Guide to the Papers of Nathaniel Pendleton 1767-1867 MS 483
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Nathaniel Pendleton Papers
1767-1867
MS 483
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.65 Linear feet (2 boxes)
Correspondence, legal, financial, and real estate material of Nathaniel Pendleton. The collection also includes correspondence and papers of his son, Edmund Henry Pendleton, and father-in-law, Dr. John Bard, as well as material relating to Pendleton's role as Alexander Hamilton's second in his duel with Aaron Burr.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical Note
1756 Nathaniel Pendleton born in Culpeper County, Virginia
1775 Joins Revolutionary Army; serves as aide-de-camp to Gen. Nathaniel Greene
1787 Serves as delegate to Constitutional Convention, but is not present at signing
1789 Appointed U.S. District Judge of Georgia
1796 Moves to New York City; marries Susan Bard
1804 Acts as Alexander Hamilton's second in his fatal duel with Aaron Burr
1821 Dies near residence in Duchess County, New York
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nathaniel Pendleton consist of correspondence, licenses and certificates, land papers, legal and financial documents, and a few family papers, 1767-1867, of jurist and Revolutionary War officer Nathaniel Pendleton of Virginia, Georgia, and New York City. Also included are documents related to Pendleton's role as Alexander Hamilton's second in his duel with Aaron Burr in 1804, maps and papers of Pendleton's father-in-law, Dr. John Bard of New York City, and papers of Pendleton's son, Edmund H. Pendleton.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following seven series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1782-1820
Series II. Legal and Real Estate documents, Receipts and Notes, 1785-1833, n.d.
Series III. Licenses to Practice Law, 1785-1833, n.d.
Series IV. Edmund Henry Pendleton Papers, 1785-1867, n.d.
Series V. John Bard Papers, 1772-1820, n.d.
Series VI. Alexander Hamilton Papers, 1793-1813, n.d.
Series VII. Indentures, 1762-1798
The materials are arranged chronologically within each series.
Bard, John, 1716-1799; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849-Trials litigation, etc.; Greene, Catharine Littlefield; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804-Death and burial; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804-Estate; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Hamilton, Elizabeth, 1758-1816; Johnson, William, 1771-1834; Mc Intyre, Arch'd (Archibald), 1772-1858; Pendleton family; Pendleton, Edmund Henry, 1788-1862; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803; Ray, Paul; Van Ness, William P. (William Peter), 1778-1826; Varaigne, Mary Jauncey de; Burr-Hamilton Duel, Weehawken, N.J., 1804; Cadastral maps; Ciphers; Ciphers (codes); Correspondence; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry-United States; Georgia-Description and travel; Licenses; Minisink region (N.Y.); New York (State)-Politics and government-1775-1865; Practice of law-Georgia; Practice of law-New York (State); Real property-Georgia; Real property-New York (State); Slaves-emancipation; Trials (Military offenses)-United States; United States-History-Revolution, 1775-1783; Wills
- Series I: Correspondence, 1782-1820
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is composed of correspondence of Nathaniel Pendleton in the period 1782-1820, divided into two subseries.
  - Subseries 1: General Correspondence, 1782-1820
    Correspondence of Nathaniel Pendleton.
    - Correspondence, 1782-1790 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1793-1816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1793-1820 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Letters from Edmund Pendleton to Nephew Nathaniel Pendleton, 1782-1801
    This series contains letters from Virginia statesman Edmund Pendleton to his nephew, Nathaniel Pendleton.
    - Letters from Edmund Pendleton to Nathaniel Pendleton, 1782-1801 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Legal and Real Estate Documents, Receipts, Notes, 1785-1833, n.d.
  This series contains documents concerning land transactions, financial matters, military and political affairs. Also included is a seventeen-page description of Georgia, written by Pendleton in 1800, entitled "A Short Account of the Sea Coast of Georgia, in Respect to Agriculture, Ship-Building, Navigation and the Timber Trade.
  - Legal and Real Estate Documents, Receipts, Notes, 1785-1833, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: Licenses to Practice Law, 1785-1867, n.d.
  This series contains Pendleton's licenses to practice law in the states of Virginia, Georgia and New York.
  - Licenses to Practice Law, 1785-1796 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Edmund Henry Pendleton (1788-1862), 1785-1867, n.d.
  This series contains the papers of Nathaniel Pendleton's son, Edmund Henry Pendleton, divided into two subseries.
  - Subseries 1. Correspondence and Legal Documents, 1816-1867, n.d.
    This subseries includes correspondence with his wife, Fanny, and Henry Clay. Also included is a document signed by Edmund H. Pendleton manumitting Paul Ray, July 5, 1822, born a slave to his father, Nathaniel Pendleton.
    - Edmund Henry Pendleton, 1816-1867, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2. Correspondence and Notes Related to Mary Jauncey de Varaigne Estate, 1785-1796
    This series contains materials concerning the settlement of the estate inherited in part by Mary Jauncey de Varaigne of Paris.
    - Correspondence and Notes Related to Mary Jauncey de Varaigne Estate, 1785-1796 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series V: John Bard (1716-1799), 1772-1820, n.d.
  This series contains the papers of Nathaniel Pendleton's father-in-law, Dr. John Bard, mainly pertaining to properties located in the Minisink Patent, land titles and transactions, and the settlement of his estate.
  - John Bard, 1772-1820, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Alexander Hamilton (1757-1804), 1793-1813, n.d.
  This series contains papers related to the death and estate of Alexander Hamilton. Materials pertaining to Pendleton's friendship with Hamilton and his role as Hamilton's second in his duel with Aaron Burr include a list of arrangements for the duel in Pendleton's hand; letters from William Van Ness inquiring as to Hamilton's condition; a report of the duel endorsed as "Facts agreed between N.P. and W.V.N."; report of a conversation between Hamilton and Judge Purdy in Albany, February 25, 1804; correspondence with Van Ness regarding publication of the duel material; obituary notice in Pendleton's hand; statement of Hamilton's pecuniary affairs, property and debts; copy of Hamilton's will; manuscripts pertaining to Hamilton's estate and to the gift of land to his family from his New England friends; and material concerning a cipher discovered by Pendleton among Hamilton's papers, along with an explanation in French.
  - Alexander Hamilton, 1793-1804 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alexander Hamilton Family Papers, 1803-1813 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Duel Material, 1804, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series VII: Indentures, 1767-1798
  This series includes six indentures for lands in New York State and Georgia.
  - Indentures, 1767-1798 (Box 2, Folder 13)